Yes, indeed.
It was one of the Days of God.
Nothing can now stop us, God willing,
and we will enter Damascus,
Hums, Qinnisrin and Jerusalem.
Well done, Abu Sulaiman.
Abu Bakr was right, may God have mercy...
May God have mercy on him and us,
when he said:
'Women could never beget the like of Khalid.'
We did not achieve victory
by the sword alone, Abu Ubaidah.
God will not cause to fail a community
that has someone
like Abu Ubaidah,
the trustee of the Muslim nation.
The clan of Makhzoom never knew
two brothers like you.
God has willed that death
will not seperate you.
To Him belongs whatever He takes.
Peace be to you until
God gathers us all to Him.
Congratulations to you
and to us all for this great victory.
May God reward you generously
for what you have done.
You are the best of Muslim women.
As for you, Umm Hakeem,
I pray to God to comfort you
after losing my cousin Ikrimah.
Submit him as an offering to God.
Muslims will cross the Yarmuk
until the end of time and say:
Here are buried Ikrimah,
as well as Ayyash Ibn Abi Rabeeah
and Salamah Ibn Hisham
and other companions of the Prophet.
Here was the beginning of Islam in Syria
and these were its keys.
Peace be to them all.
You will be all right, father.
Peace be to the people in the tent.
May I come in?
Come in, Abu Sulaiman.
You will be all right, Abu Sufyan.
You have made your apology to God.
Make your eye an offering to Him.
It is His. I would not mind if I lose both eyes.
now that God has honoured us with this victory.
As for avenging my eye, it will be
by taking Damascus soon, Abu Sulaiman.
Now that the Byzantines are demoralized,
you must not let them rest.
We will not, God willing.
How do you rate what my son,
Yazeed, has done?
He has fought well
and honoured his pledge to God.
It is right that you consider him the apple of your eye.
Which eye, Abu Sulaiman?
You will be all right. You will.
Lie down, son, until you recover.
I am all right.
I praise God who has seen me fighting
for God's cause.
next to my father, Suhail Ibn Amr.
I would have loved to have joined
my brother, Abdullah, as a martyr.
But God has willed otherwise.
How much Islam has changed us!
I can see myself in those old days
when I used to say to people:
Do not alter the religion of your forefathers.
Follow their way and stick to their practices.
Now I praise God for guiding me
to follow my two sons into Islam.
I am not ashamed
that they took the lead over me.
My Lord, bestow Your grace
on my son, Abdullah
May God have mercy on you, Abu Ubaidah.
Why have you kept the news from me
so that I hear it from others?
May God bestow His mercy on Abu Bakr.
To God we belong and to Him
we shall return.
He was certainly dearer to me than Umar,
but Umar is now the Caliph,
and God requires me to obey him.
There would not have been anything amiss
had I obeyed his order straightaway.
and become one of the soldiers,
to fight under the banner of our commander,
Abu Ubaidah.
I am not here to fight for Umar's sake,
but for the sake of Umar's Lord.
I wish you had told me right away and did not feel any embarrassment.
Yes, indeed. I felt very embarrassed.
I did not wish to spoil your delight
at your great victory,
when you are God's own drawn sword.
Abu Sulaiman, God knows that I seek
nothing of the glory of this world.
We are brothers, fulfilling God's orders.
You retain your position with me.
We shall not plan or fight
without your guidance.
Do not worry, Abu Ubaidah. How could I
disobey you when you have been a believer.
and follower of Islam long before me,
and when it was God's messenger who
called you the 'trustee of the Muslim nation'?
Now, I would like you
and all present to witness
that I am dedicating myself to God's cause,
and I will never oppose you.
Your majesty.
You are aware of what befell us at Yarmuk
Certain matters have occurred
at Constantinople
which require me to go back without delay.
I will monitor from there what happens
here in Syria from now on.
I will do my best to send you
all the reinforcements we can.
Repel the Muslims and keep them busy
at msuch as you can.
Our losses of army personnel
cannot be made good in a short while.
God decides what He will.
Farewell, Syria.
Farewell. I shall never see you again.
How much for one dirham?
Two small measures.
Two small ones for a dirham!
Why the high price?
I do not force anyone. Whoever finds
my price high can go to someone else.
If sonemoe else will sell for less,
you cannot sell your goods for this price.
Otherwise, you will be without customers.
I know what you are doing.
when farmers bring their grains to Madinah,
you beat the people to them,
buying all they bring so as
to make it a monopoly.
You withhold the goods from widows
and poor people.
By God, there will be no monopoly
in our market.
There will be no monopoly in our market.
Whoever brings goods to Madinah
to sell to all people...
will be Umar's guest
He can sell as he wants
and holds what he wants.
Sell four small measures for one dirham,
or else leave our market.
Otherwise, my punishment
will be administered.
Pardon me. I did not know
that it is unjust and forbidden.
And that too?
To all people in the market.
Anyone who wants to sell goods in our
market must acquire good knowledge
of what is permissible and what
is forbidden in trade transactions,
so that his work has no element of injustice
Otherwise he may well be guilty of usury
and illegal earnings,
whether willingly or unwillingly.
Do you hear me?
You should also know that I shall be
appointing officials in all markets,
to watch and monitor
and to arbitrate in disagreements.
No one should keep silent
when suffering injustice.
To suppress the truth
is to be like a dumb devil.
Happy news, Ameer Al-Mu'mineen.
Al-Yarmuk.
It is a great victory granted by God.
Here is a messenger from Abu Ubaidah.
All praise be to God; all praise be to God.
All praise be to God!
Now that God has granted victory
to the people of Yarmuk,
and has demoralized the Byzantines,
our friends are heading to Damascus.
You should help them by thanking God
for what He has given us all.
When you do, God will bestow
more grace on them and us.
All praise be to God.
Some of you may say:
why has Ameer Al-Mu'mineen relieved
Khalid of the command of the army in Syria,
when we know how much he has achieved?
You should know that I have not done so as
a result of any grudge or for any misdeed.
My decision is based on three reasons.
The first is that I often heard people saying:
no one can replace Khalid
or match his achievements,
or that without him this
or that would not have been achieved.
Hence, I feared that people should
give him a much higher status.
I want them to know that it is God
who determines everything.
What if Khalid dies,
will Islam be much weaker?
Will God's promise come to and end?
Before him, the best of mankind,
Muhammad, God's messenger, died
and the faith progressed according
to God's promise
A nation that attaches its affairs
to one man is bound to fail
When that man goes,
the whole system falls.
The second reason...
is that Khalid differs with me on the question
of the authority of governors & commanders.
He sticks to his view and will not budge.
He feels that a governor is independent,
and should conduct the affairs
of his area as he thinks fit,
without reference to the Caliph.
For my part, I believe that the Caliph
is accountable to God
for his own actions and those
of his governors and commanders.
The third reason is the governors
and commanders
do not only lead armies and plan battles.
We would have preferred
to avoid war altogether,
because our task is to provide guidance
for people and to advocate Islam.
Governors and commanders are also
responsible to manage people's affairs,
ensure justice, administer rights
and look after their subjects.
Syria is about to be part of the Islamic state,
when political management becomes
more important than war management.
Abu Ubaidah has the advantage
of a longer companionship with the Prophet.
Besides, he is a devout believer who reflects
on things, and he is kind to all people.
If Khalid is under him
and employs his military talent
in accordance with Abu Ubaidah's policy,
we are sure that the two
will perfect each other.
We can guarantee that the sword will not
dictate matters of management and policy.
This is a basic principle of government.
I have given this explanation so that
there will not be much talk about it
and to remove any suspicion
from people's minds.
This is what I have felt.
If I am right, it is only by God's grace,
and if I am wrong,
the fault is mine.
Prepare yourselves for a long siege.
I think we better divide our troops
to watch all five gates:
Khalid, myself...
Who is the commander?
Speak, may God give you guidance.
Amr, Yazeed, and Shurahbeel:
each mans one gate.
Who is the commander?
Speak, may God give you guidance.
We belong to the Arabs of Syria,
the Jafnah clan of Ghassan.
Good people and good kings.
Before Islam, our people were
always hosted well...
among you when they came
with their trade caravans.
This is why we have come to you now.
Although we follow the same religion
as the Byzantines,
we share with you our ancestry
and language.
We hate them for their dictatorial rule.
They treat us with arrogance,
when we are people of noble descent
and the owners of the land.
We have noted your fair rule
in the areas of Syria under your authority.
Therefore, we would like to join you.
We can command large forces.
In addition, we have knowledge
of the machinery suited for siege,
like mangonels. We learnt these
from the Byzantines.
We can help you with manufacturing them,
if you wish.
If you accept our offer
and we honour our commitment,
what do we get in return?
We will honour our commitment,
and you will be under our care.
We will observe God's unjunctions and the
instructions given to us by God's messenger,
his first successor
and Ameer Al-Mu'mineen.
You shall not be force to convert to Islam.
Your lives and property would be safe.
will leave you to run your land
as you please,
with full autonomy as long as you
administer justice in your land.
If you wish to refer anything to us
for judgement,
we will give such judgement according
to our law which applies to us.
We do not impose on you any tribute
or land tax more than you can pay.
The tribute we call jizyah is less than
the zakat which is a duty applicable to us
and an act of worship.
Were we to impose it on you in line
with what is a duty to Muslims,
it would be taken as an act of religious
imposition. This is forbidden in Islam.
God says: 'No compulsion is admissible
in matters of religion'.
We also pledge to you that we will
protect you from our common enemies.
If we cannot, we take nothing from you.
We accept these terms.
As for provisions and supplies,
we have enough to last us six months.
Soon winter will come and they
cannot tolerate the cold weather,
considering that they come from
a hot desert climate.
They do not have the machines
used in siege which we know.
This means that we are safe within the city.
Return the milk to him.
This milk has been adulterated with water.
Do you not know that such cheating
is forbidden and God punishes for it
Give her back his money.
If you wish, take the milk home
and give it to your family.
If you do not, I will pour it here
and give orders for you to be flogged
in front of the people in the market.
If you do it again, I will kick you out
of the market and punish you severely.
Why do you interfere in my work?
Who are you to give orders?
All glory to God. Cheating and arrogance
Pardon me, Ameer Al-Mu'mineen.
but this woman...
Didn't I promise to appoint officials
to watch how business is conducted
and to settle disputes between people
This woman is As-Shifa Bint Abdullah. I have
appointed her as controller of your market.
Whatever she rules is my ruling.
Any punishment she orders is my order.
If any of you is unsure of what is permissible
and what is forbidden regarding anything
should ask her.
she is competent,
and she enjoys my full trust.
What have you ruled in this man's case?
That he gives his milk to his own family,
or we will spill it.
If he does it again, we flog him
and kick him out of the market.
Had I seen him first
I would have flogged him first,
but now we approve As-Shifa's ruling.
Obey her.
Now return to your work.
Return the milk to him.
What is this?
A blessing from God.
Rather, punishment by God.
I say to all of you:
guard yourselves against getting fat,
because that will make you slacken
for prayer, and it spoils your bodies,
and brings you illnesses.
Eat moderately, for that helps you to be well
and keeps you from extravagance.
You will be better able
to conduct you worship
Your highness, Princess Buran.
At last, Commander Rustom.
You haven't let me down.
When I wrote to you in Khurasan,
I was certain that you are the one to save our kingdom.
I would not have undertaken
this responsibility
except for the fat that the scheming
of Queen Azarmidukht
and her commander Siyawakhsh
threatened to do away with all that
our forefathers have built
over a thousand years.
Then these noblemen grouped together and
placed the fate of the kingdom in my hand.
They know that I do not want to be queen,
but I want to save Persia.
Therefore, it was necessary to get rid
of Azarmidukht and her commander,
and to put and end to this long struggle
for the Persian throne.
This has been accomplished.
We have got rid of Azarmidukht
and Siyawakhsh the murderer.
My father was the first victim.
Nothing pleased me more than killing him
in revenge of my father
and for what he perpetrated.
These noblemen have done well to join you.
I am one of them to serve you.
Just give me your orders.
This is not the milk of my she-camel.
It tastes different.
Indeed, Ameer Al-Mu'mineed.
Where did you get it, man?
Your she-camel, Ameer Al-Mu'mineen,
was left dry by her calf.
I milked for you one
of the she-camels of the state.
How dare you give me a drink of fire?
Are you not one of the Muslim community?
You have the right to your share in
the state property like any one of them.
It is just a drink of milk.
Nothing of the state property
is permissible for me other
than what I get the people's approval of.
Then get them to approve what you need
for your living and your family.
We have suffered much since you
have taken charge of the state.
You have abandoned your business
to attend to the affairs of the people.
We do not find enough to eat, and no
allowance has been given to you so far.
How shall we live?
They could not have reached
this stage without our help.
Our great kings have gone,
and their throne became
the property of the winner.
Every prince tries to overthrow
the incumbent.
Little do they realize that they may lose
the throne itself ot the Arabs.
Yes, commander.
Unless we are reunited, we will soon
see them besieging Al-Mada'in.
Could a day come when the Arabs are
the rules of Persia and we are their slaves?
Isn't death better than that?
Yes, Your highness. Death is better.
Well, make up your minds
before it is too late.
We have heard that they have raised another
army which is on its way to Al-Heerah
to join their army already there.
You know, Your highness, that the surviving
descendant of Khosrau Parves
has disappeared, fearing for his life,
after Shirweih killed his father the Khosrau
and his father's male offspring.
Then we plunged into what you know
of the other princes' rivalries for the throne.
They resorted to treachery and internal war.
Khosrau's descendants have the rightful
claim to the throne of Persia.
However, the present time
and circumstances
do not allow us a chance to search
for them and appointing one of them.
You are the only one who can unite us now.
I think you should assume the throne
for a period of ten years,
so that we can get rid of that Arab threat
and regain stability.
Then the kingdom may go back
to the descendants of Khosrau.
Yes, this is right.
If this is the only way,
then Commander Rustom is my minister
and the Commander-in-Chief.
I authorize him to manage the affairs
of the state on war footing.
Al-Fairuzan will be his deputy,
to manage the affairs of the state
when Rustom leads his armies.
Your throne, your majesty.
I pledge to you that I will defend
it with all my power.
The destiny of Persia is now in your hand,
minister and commander!
I promised you that I would take nothing
from the treasury
while I have enough of my own.
Now my money is gone.
What am I allowed to have
from the treasury?
Ameer al-Mu'mineen knows this
better than us.
Say what you think. we either accept
or tell you what we think.
The mount I need to travel
for pilgrimage or Umrah,
and my two robes for summer
and two robes for winter,
the food for my family,
and my share as a Muslim individual.
This is fair.
Do you all agree to this?
Yes.
Ameer al-Mu'mineen, the one who
is most entitled to have good food,
comfortable mount, fine clothes is you.
By God I do not think you said this
in honesty to God.
You only said it to have some favour
with me. I used to think well of you.
Do you know, man,
what my standing with these people is?
It is like a group of people travelling
together. They gave their expenses
to one of them and told him
to look after them.
It is permissible for him to take
of it something extra for himself?
No.
This is my case with them.
Why is this man walking in such a way?
Since when has devotion meant
a faint walk and a miserable look?
You are killing our religion, may God kill you.
Walk upright and show the dignity of Islam.
How come that some people think
that devotion means looking dead,
in the midst of the living?
Why would they speak softly,
bend their heads when walking,
and drop their heads
and shoulders in prayer?
Do they not fear that they may be
suspected of hypocrisy?
Hypocrisy may be in a show of piety
just as it may be in arrogance?
Both aim to show others
that one is better than them,
either in religion
or in what relates to the present life.
We have learnt that the new Muslim army
has not arrived in Iraq yet.
Their resident commander
at Al-Heerah, I mean...
Al-Muthanna
Yes
He has only a few thousand soldiers.
We better attack them
before the new reinforcements arrive.
We will send two armies: one goes
to Al-Heerah, commanded by Jaban.
The other army joins the force
between the two rivers.
Its commander will be Nersi.
I thought you would go
at the head of the armies.
No.
My plan is to send several armies,
one following the other.
This is harder for the enemy.
I fear that the princes, or commanders,
might be plotting against Princess Buran.
We have seen what others did.
They represent a greater danger
to the state than the Muslims.
I will discharge both responsibilities.
Let no one entertain any doubt.
God is supreme.
Your face tells me that your news
is not good. Say it.
It is the worst news.
Jaban's army has been defeated
at Al-Namariq,
then Nersi's army was defeated first
at Al-Saqqatiyyah in Kaskar,
then at Baruka.
The Muslims then smashed Jalinus's army
which set out to reinforce Nersi.
The Muslims defeated four of our armies
in less than a month.
They regained the entire countryside
before conquering the city of Kaskar.
What has happened to Persia
which had previously defeated all corners?
Where are our soldiers who used to
spread panic wherever they went?
No. The fault is not with the soldiers;
It is with the commanders who want to
lead the soldiers to great victories
while they remain in their palaces here
at Al-Mada'in.
You mean Rustom.
Yes, Rustom.
Your majesty made him
Commander-in-chief and minister,
assigning to him the task of managing
the affairs of the state.
I advised him to raise the armies
and go out himself, but he refused.
Now we have the outcome,
one defeat after another.
The Muslims are now in control
of the whole of Iraq, north to south.
Show us how they work.
The traitors!
By God, if the Muslims are turned back,
I shall punish all Syrian Arabs
who have helped them.
I shall crucify them in every city.
They have seen their brethern outside
the city siding with the Muslims.
I have no doubt that some of them here
communicate to their Arab brothers
outside news of what take place here
in Damascus.
Haven't I ordered that spies
should move among them?
Whoever they determine to be favouring
their own people over us
should be made a lesson to all others.
I have placed you ahead
of all commanders and princes.
I went against other people's advice.
I was content to allow you to manage
matters on a war footing.
I do not wish to say that I am let down,
but... such successive defeats!
The war is still evenly balanced,
your majesty
I am the one who is let down by Nersi,
Jaban, Jalinus and the tax collectors.
But you are the commander-in-chief, and
whatever these do will be attributed to you,
in victory or defeat.
You know that some princes and
commanders are watching what you do.
They have started whispering.
I do not know how to respond to them.
It is al-Fairuzan. I know that he is
the one who tries to undermine me.
He is jealous of my standing with you,
and would prefer that I should dissapear,
even if this meant that Persia is gone as well.
Don't you see, your majesty?
It is because of this that I preferred
that I do not go myself at this stage
to fight the Muslims.
If I did, I would be playing into his
and his friends' hands.
They would be able to plot against me
when I am away.
If they did when we are at war,
then the whole future of Persia is gone.
If you want me to sack him now,
that will only precipitate what you fear.
You know that he has supporters.
If he is sacked, they will revolt
against me and you.
That will be the end of Persia.
What is needed is that you should achieve
a great victory over the Muslims.
Victory in the battlefield will be a victory
for us over those who have ambitions here.
The two go hand in hand.
There is no other way.